<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="AMW_AnnaJCooper_Scene1_Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <titlePage>
        <title>CHRISTMAS BELLS</title>
        <desc>A One Act Play for Children</desc>
        <prep>by</prep>
        <author>ANNA J. COOPER</author>
        <charList>
            <desc>DRAMATIS PERSONAE</desc>
            <spk>HANNAH</spk>, aged eleven, “the little Mother,” who has the care of her two
            sisters, while the Mother works by the day, away from home. The Father is a soldier,
            across the sea. 
            <spk>NANNETTE</spk>, aged eight 
            <spk>ANNIKINS</spk>, aged four 
            <spk>THE THREE KINGS</spk>,— 
            <spk>GASPARD</spk>, a European, 
            <spk>MELCHOIR</spk>, an Asiatic,
            <spk>BALTHAZAR</spk>, an African. 
            <spk>CHORUS OF ANGELS</spk>
            <spk>CHORUS OF SHEPHERDS</spk>
            <spk>SUNSHINE CLUB OF THE COMMUNITY SERVICE</spk>. Soldiers. Red 
            <spk>CROSS NURSES</spk>
        </charList>
    </titlePage>
    
    <scene n="1">
        <sceneNumb>SCENE I</sceneNumb>
        <sd>Before the curtain rises, Christinas chimes arc heard, playing distinctly,—“Christians,
            awake! Salute the happy morn, Whereon the Savior of mankind was born!* At the close of
            the chimes a pause of jo seconds absolute silence; after which there sounds shrill and
            clear a single stroke of a bell. The curtain rises, disclosing a room of a humble family
            of three children. “ The little Mother" is busy about the evening meal; Nannette is
            setting the table; Annikins, on the floor, cuts pictures for paper dolls.</sd>
        
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. What are the bells ringing for? </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. Why, don’t you know dear? They're ringing for the
            Christmas Child—for His birthday. This is Christmas Eve!</dial>
        
        <dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. Is Christ Child coming here? </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Thoughtfully)</sd> Why yes, Annikins. He will
            come to us if we try to be kind and good. </dial
        >
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. Sister, can’t we possibly have a Christmas tree
            this year ? </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. I’m afraid not, deary. But we’ll try to be happy
            just the same. We’ll play “make believe’’ and make each other wonderful presents. It's
            lots of fun! And write letters to Daddy, and we’ll ask the Christ Child to bring Daddy
            safe home to us, and then mother will not have to work so hard down town. And we’ll ask
            the Christ Child to bring us sweet Peace and Good Will. Because lie is the Prince of
            Peace, and that’s what He is coming for. And then I s'pose we ought to pray for
            Democracy, ’cause that’s what Daddy is fighting for. </dial>
        
        <pn>2</pn>
        
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. What is Democracy? </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. I’m not sure I know, little sister. It’s kind of
            hard to understand. But it must be what the Christ Child wants every where in the
            world—for it means every body will be good and kind to every body and there'll not be
            any poor people who can’t get enough to eat, nor any unkind people who scorn and hate.
            Just all the world will love each other like you and I and Annikins love one another.
            Every body will be helping to make the world good and pleasant for every body else and
            so the Christ Child will come back to us again and He will be our Big Brother and all
            the people will be brothers ’cause you see they will all be His brothers. Come now
            Annikins, put away your paper dollies. Supper is ready. <sd>(She smoothes the child's
                hair, examines hands and face to see that they arc clean, and lifts her into a
                high-chair at the table. The others take their places and, with bowed heads and
                folded hands, sing the grace)</sd> — God is great and God is good, And we thank thee
            for this food; By thy hand must we be fed, Give us, Lord, our daily bread. Amen. </dial>
        
        <dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. Pass the sugar! <sd>(correcting herself)</sd>
            Excuse me sister, please pass the sugar! </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. Oo-h Annikins! [Don't take quite so much, love!
            Uncle Sam says we can't have any more sugar till next month! </dial>
        
        <dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. <sd>(Confidentially to her big sister)</sd> you
            tell the Christmas Child / want some sugar,—hear? <sd>(Carol singers are heard
                outside)</sd>
        </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. Hush, child, listen. It’s the carol singers! </dial>
        
        <dial speak="CAROL SINGERS"><spk>CAROL SINGERS</spk>. Christmas where children are hopeful
            and gay, Christmas where old men are patient and gray, Christmas with peace, like a dove
            in its flight, Over brave men in the thick of the fight. Everywhere, everywhere,
            Christmas tonight! Immediately after the carols the Sunshine Club come bursting in,
            covered with snow. The boys tc-car muffllers. Some have ice-skates hung over their
            shoulders. Two of the boys lug in a tree all ready to set up. The girls have their arms
            full of trinkets for the tree and presents for the children. They are bubbling over with
            spirits and gayly shouting,—“Merry Christmas Hannah! Merry Christmas Nanncttc! Hello,
            Annikins! Merry Christmas!" Their leader gives the child a bear-hug, and presents her
            with a wonderful doll, almost as big as the four-year-old herself. Nan net te gets a
            beautiful red dress and a string of beads. The children clap their hands in glee. While
            dressing the tree they sing. There’s a wonderful tree a wonderful tree The happy
            children rejoice to see. Spreading its branches year by year It comes from the forest to
            flourish here. Oh this beautiful tree with its branches wide Is always blooming at
            Christmas T ide; And a voice is telling its boughs among Of the Shepherds’ watch and the
            Angels’ song; Of a holv Babe in the manger low— The beautiful story of long ago— When a
            radiant star threw its beams so wide To herald the earliest Christmas Tide. <sd>(Joining
                hands, and singing, they dance around the tree)</sd>
        </dial>
        
        <pn>4</pn>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(A little shyly at first)</sd> Oh thank you!
            Thank you so much girls. W hat a beautiful tree! Oh, we are so happy—I had no idea we
            would have a tree! </dial>
        
        <dial speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>1st SUNSHINE GIRL</spk>. <sd>(Hanging a small doll on the
            tree)</sd> Here is a baby-doll for Annikins; skates for Xannette. And here, little
            Mother, is a gay peasant-kerchief and a picture storybook for you. I know you’ll read
            the stories to the rest. Hannah never keeps anything all for herself! </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Somewhat embarrassed)</sd> Oh girls, I—I can’t
            tell you how much—Oh, I mean you are so good and kind—I just don’t know how to thank
            you. </dial>
        
        <dial speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>1st SUNSHINE GIRL</spk>. Oh don’t thank us at all, just
            thank the Christ Child! </dial>
        
        <dial speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>2nd SUNSHINE GIRL</spk>. All who love the Christ Child are
            trying to make little children happy tonight, don't you know? We don’t want a single
            child to be forgotten. His love will warm and cheer the loneliest child on earth. </dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Thoughtfully)</sd> Yes. All for the Christ
            Child who was born tonight. To love Him is to love all little children. </dial>
        
        <dial speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>SUNSHINE GIRLS</spk>. <sd>(Putting on their wraps, waving
            Merry Christmas to all; shaking hands affectionately with Hannah)</sd>. Good night
            everybody! Be good children! Good night,—good night!</dial>
        
        <dial speak="THE CHILDREN"><spk>THE CHILDREN</spk>. Good night! Merry Christmas! </dial>
        
        <dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. <sd>(Piping up)</sd> Au revoir-au revoir!
            <sd>(Exit S.S. Club laughing and throwing kisses. A pause)</sd></dial>
        
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. What a wonderful tree! <sd>(They examine the
            presents)</sd></dial>
        
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Bustling to hide her emotion)</sd> Come now
            <sd>(takes Annikins by the hand)</sd>. The Christ Child has sent us perfectly lovely
            friends and I am so glad you have your Christmas tree after a ll! Kneel down children.
            Annikins, put your hands together. <sd>(They all kneel and repeat a prayer)</sd> Oh holy
            Child of Bethlehem! Descend to us we pray; Cast out our sin and enter in. Be born in us
            today. We hear the Christmas angels The great glad tidings tell; Oh, come to us—Abide
            with us, Our Lord, Emanuel. <sd>(During the prayer the stage is gradually darkened, so
                that the children are no longer visible)</sd>
        </dial>
        
    </scene>
</xml>
