<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="VanWoert_Final_Projecct_Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<xml>
    <titlePage>
        <title>CHRISTMAS BELLS</title>
        <desc>A One Act Play for Children</desc>
        <prep>by</prep>
        <author>ANNA J. COOPER</author>
        <charList>
            <desc>DRAMATIS PERSONAE</desc>
            <spk>HANNAH</spk>, aged eleven, “the little Mother,” who has the care of her two
            sisters, while the Mother works by the day, away from home. The Father is a soldier,
            across the sea. <spk>NANNETTE</spk>, aged eight <spk>ANNIKINS</spk>, aged four <spk>THE
                THREE KINGS</spk>,— <spk>GASPARD</spk>, a European, <spk>MELCHOIR</spk>, an Asiatic,
                <spk>BALTHAZAR</spk>, an African. <spk>CHORUS OF ANGELS</spk>
            <spk>CHORUS OF SHEPHERDS</spk>
            <spk>SUNSHINE CLUB OF THE COMMUNITY SERVICE</spk>. Soldiers. Red <spk>CROSS NURSES</spk>
        </charList>
    </titlePage>
    <scene n="1">
        <sceneNumb>SCENE I</sceneNumb>
        <sd>Before the curtain rises, Christinas chimes arc heard, playing distinctly,—“Christians,
            awake! Salute the happy morn, Whereon the Savior of mankind was born!* At the close of
            the chimes a pause of jo seconds absolute silence; after which there sounds shrill and
            clear a single stroke of a bell. The curtain rises, disclosing a room of a humble family
            of three children. “ The little Mother" is busy about the evening meal; Nannette is
            setting the table; Annikins, on the floor, cuts pictures for paper dolls.</sd>
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. What are the bells ringing for? </dial><dial
            speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. Why, don’t you know dear? They're ringing for the
            Christmas Child—for His birthday. This is Christmas Eve!</dial>
        <dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. Is Christ Child coming here? </dial><dial
            speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Thoughtfully)</sd> Why yes, Annikins. He will
            come to us if we try to be kind and good. </dial><dial speak="NANNETTE"
                ><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. Sister, can’t we possibly have a Christmas tree this year ?
            </dial><dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. I’m afraid not, deary. But we’ll try to
            be happy just the same. We’ll play “make believe’’ and make each other wonderful
            presents. It's lots of fun! And write letters to Daddy, and we’ll ask the Christ Child
            to bring Daddy safe home to us, and then mother will not have to work so hard down town.
            And we’ll ask the Christ Child to bring us sweet Peace and Good Will. Because lie is the
            Prince of Peace, and that’s what He is coming for. And then I s'pose we ought to pray
            for Democracy, ’cause that’s what Daddy is fighting for. </dial><pn>2</pn>
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. What is Democracy? </dial><dial speak="HANNAH"
                ><spk>HANNAH</spk>. I’m not sure I know, little sister. It’s kind of hard to
            understand. But it must be what the Christ Child wants every where in the world—for it
            means every body will be good and kind to every body and there'll not be any poor people
            who can’t get enough to eat, nor any unkind people who scorn and hate. Just all the
            world will love each other like you and I and Annikins love one another. Every body will
            be helping to make the world good and pleasant for every body else and so the Christ
            Child will come back to us again and He will be our Big Brother and all the people will
            be brothers ’cause you see they will all be His brothers. Come now Annikins, put away
            your paper dollies. Supper is ready. <sd>(She smoothes the child's hair, examines hands
                and face to see that they arc clean, and lifts her into a high-chair at the table.
                The others take their places and, with bowed heads and folded hands, sing the
                grace)</sd> — God is great and God is good, And we thank thee for this food; By thy
            hand must we be fed, Give us, Lord, our daily bread. Amen. </dial><dial speak="ANNIKINS"
                ><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. Pass the sugar! <sd>(correcting herself)</sd> Excuse me
            sister, please pass the sugar! </dial><dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. Oo-h
            Annikins! [Don't take quite so much, love! Uncle Sam says we can't have any more sugar
            till next month! </dial><dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. <sd>(Confidentially
                to her big sister)</sd> you tell the Christmas Child / want some sugar,—hear?
                <sd>(Carol singers are heard outside)</sd>
        </dial><dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. Hush, child, listen. It’s the carol singers!
            </dial><dial speak="CAROL SINGERS"><spk>CAROL SINGERS</spk>. Christmas where children
            are hopeful and gay, Christmas where old men are patient and gray, Christmas with peace,
            like a dove in its flight, Over brave men in the thick of the fight. Everywhere,
            everywhere, Christmas tonight! Immediately after the carols the Sunshine Club come
            bursting in, covered with snow. The boys tc-car muffllers. Some have ice-skates hung
            over their shoulders. Two of the boys lug in a tree all ready to set up. The girls have
            their arms full of trinkets for the tree and presents for the children. They are
            bubbling over with spirits and gayly shouting,—“Merry Christmas Hannah! Merry Christmas
            Nanncttc! Hello, Annikins! Merry Christmas!" Their leader gives the child a bear-hug,
            and presents her with a wonderful doll, almost as big as the four-year-old herself. Nan
            net te gets a beautiful red dress and a string of beads. The children clap their hands
            in glee. While dressing the tree they sing. There’s a wonderful tree a wonderful tree
            The happy children rejoice to see. Spreading its branches year by year It comes from the
            forest to flourish here. Oh this beautiful tree with its branches wide Is always
            blooming at Christmas T ide; And a voice is telling its boughs among Of the Shepherds’
            watch and the Angels’ song; Of a holv Babe in the manger low— The beautiful story of
            long ago— When a radiant star threw its beams so wide To herald the earliest Christmas
            Tide. <sd>(Joining hands, and singing, they dance around the tree)</sd>
        </dial><pn>4</pn>
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(A little shyly at first)</sd> Oh thank you!
            Thank you so much girls. W hat a beautiful tree! Oh, we are so happy—I had no idea we
            would have a tree! </dial><dial speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>1st SUNSHINE GIRL</spk>.
                <sd>(Hanging a small doll on the tree)</sd> Here is a baby-doll for Annikins; skates
            for Xannette. And here, little Mother, is a gay peasant-kerchief and a picture storybook
            for you. I know you’ll read the stories to the rest. Hannah never keeps anything all for
            herself! </dial><dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Somewhat embarrassed)</sd>
            Oh girls, I—I can’t tell you how much—Oh, I mean you are so good and kind—I just don’t
            know how to thank you. </dial><dial speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>1st SUNSHINE GIRL</spk>.
            Oh don’t thank us at all, just thank the Christ Child! </dial><dial
            speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>2nd SUNSHINE GIRL</spk>. All who love the Christ Child are
            trying to make little children happy tonight, don't you know? We don’t want a single
            child to be forgotten. His love will warm and cheer the loneliest child on earth.
            </dial><dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Thoughtfully)</sd> Yes. All for the
            Christ Child who was born tonight. To love Him is to love all little children.
            </dial><dial speak="SUNSHINE GIRL"><spk>SUNSHINE GIRLS</spk>. <sd>(Putting on their
                wraps, waving Merry Christmas to all; shaking hands affectionately with
            Hannah)</sd>. Good night everybody! Be good children! Good night,—good night!</dial>
        <dial speak="THE CHILDREN"><spk>THE CHILDREN</spk>. Good night! Merry Christmas!
            </dial><dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. <sd>(Piping up)</sd> Au revoir-au
            revoir! <sd>(Exit S.S. Club laughing and throwing kisses. A pause)</sd></dial>
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>. What a wonderful tree! <sd>(They examine the
                presents)</sd></dial>
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>. <sd>(Bustling to hide her emotion)</sd> Come now
                <sd>(takes Annikins by the hand)</sd>. The Christ Child has sent us perfectly lovely
            friends and I am so glad you have your Christmas tree after a ll! Kneel down children.
            Annikins, put your hands together. <sd>(They all kneel and repeat a prayer)</sd> Oh holy
            Child of Bethlehem! Descend to us we pray; Cast out our sin and enter in. Be born in us
            today. We hear the Christmas angels The great glad tidings tell; Oh, come to us—Abide
            with us, Our Lord, Emanuel. <sd>(During the prayer the stage is gradually darkened, so
                that the children are no longer visible)</sd>
        </dial></scene>
    <scene n="2">
        <sceneNumb>SCENE II</sceneNumb>
        <desc>The Children's Dream City.</desc>
        <dial speak="CHRISTMAS ANNODOMINI"><spk>CHRISTMAS ANNODOMINI</spk>. Two strokes of a bell.
            On the screen a still life night scene of the City of Bethlehem. Shepherds with flocks
            in the middle distance chorus by radio transcription: </dial><dial speak="HYMN"
                ><spk>HYMN</spk>. <desc>(Chorus or transcription)</desc> O little town of Bethlehem,
            How still we see thee lie! Above thy deep and dreamless sleep The silent stars go by;
            Yet in thy dark streets shineth The everlasting L ight; The hopes and fears of all the
            years Are met in thee tonight. <pn>6</pn> For Christ is born of Mary, And gathered all
            above While mortals sleep, the angels keep Their watch of wondering love. O morning
            stars together Proclaim the holy birth, And praises sing to God the King And peace to
            men on earth! How silently, how silently The wondrous gift is given! So God imparts to
            human hearts The blessings of His heaven. No ear may hear his coming, But, in this world
            of sin, Where meek souls will receive Him, still The dear Christ enters in.</dial><dial
            speak="HYMN"><spk> HYMN</spk>. <desc>(Chorus or transcription)</desc> While shepherds
            watched their flock by night, All seated on the ground, The angel of the Lord came down,
            And glory shone around. “Fear not,” he said, for mighty dread Had seized their troubled
            mind; “Glad tidings of great joy I bring To you and all mankind.” <sd>(A strong white
                light is thrown on the stage. A shining Angel descends and sings)</sd>
        </dial><dial speak="ANGEL"><spk>ANGEL</spk>. “From Heaven above to earth I come To bring
            glad news to every home; Glad tidings of great joy I bring Whereof I now do tell and
            sing. To you tonight is born a child <pn>7</pn> Of Mary chosen Mother mildThis little
            child of lowly birth Shall be the Joy of all the Earth. <sd>(There appears suddenly from
                all sides a throng of angels who sing in chorus)</sd>
        </dial><dial speak="ANGELS"><spk>ANGELS</spk>. All glory be to God on high. And to the earth
            be peace. Good will henceforth from heaven to men Begin and never cease. For
            </dial><dial speak="CHORUS OF ANGELS"><spk>CHORUS OF ANGELS</spk>, “Glory to God:,y from
            Handel's Messiah may be used if preferred. Angels disappear suddenly <sd>(effected by
                manipulation of lights)</sd>. Enter, left back, Shepherds wearing loose tunics,
            carrying crooks, and singing:</dial>
        <dial speak="SHEPHERDS"><spk>SHEPHERDS</spk>. Hark ! the herald angels sing Glory to the
            new-born King; Peace on earth and mercy mild, God and sinners reconciled! Joyful, all ye
            nations, rise, Join the triumph of the skies; With the angelic host proclaim, Christ is
            born in Bethlehem! <sd>(Exeunt Shepherds right. The stage is dark. There appears, dimly
                at first, a star just visible in the darkness. As the star grows brighter the three
                Kings, L, back, pass to the front, R, singing)</sd>: </dial><dial speak="THE KINGS"
                ><spk>THE KINGS</spk>. We three Kings of Orient are, <pn>8</pn> Bearing gifts we
            traverse afar, Field and fountain, Moor and mountain, Following yonder Star.
                <desc>(Refrain)</desc> O Star of wonder—star of night— Star with royal beauty
            bright, Westward leading, still proceeding, Guide us to thy perfect light. </dial><dial
            speak="GASPARD"><spk>GASPARD</spk>. Born a King on Bethlehem’s plain, Gold I bring to
            crown Him again, King forever, ceasing never Over us all to reign.</dial>
        <dial speak="MELCHIOR"><spk>MELCHIOR</spk>. Frankincense to offer have I— Incense owns a
            Deity nigh. Prayer and praising, all men raising, Worship Him—God on high. </dial><dial
            speak="BALTHAZAR"><spk>BALTHAZAR</spk>. Myrrh is mine; its bitter perfume Breathes a
            life of gathering gloom; Sorrowing, sighing, bleeding, dying, Sealed in the stone-cold
            tomb. <desc>(Refrain)</desc>
        </dial><dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. Glorious now behold Him arise, King and
            God and Sacrifice. Alleluia, alleluia! Earth to heaven replies. <pn>9</pn>
            <desc>(Refrain)</desc>
            <sd>(As the Kings leave, the stage is again dark. The star alone is seen, in the middle
                distance. Gradually one spot begins to glow till, in the full radiance, is seen the
                group around the manger cradle <desc>(based on Correggio's Holy Night)</desc>. While
                the Chorus sings softly, the Shepherds enter and adore; later the Kings)</sd>
        </dial><dial speak="ANGELS"><spk>ANGELS</spk>. Holy night, Silent Night! All is calm all is
            bright Round yon Virgin Mother and Child. Holy infant, so tender and mild. Sleep in
            heavenly peace! Silent Night, Holy Night, Shepherds quake at the sight, Glories stream
            from Heaven afar. Heavenly hosts sing Alleluia, Christ the Savior is born. Silent Night,
            Holy Night, Son of God, love’s pure light Radiant beams from thy holy face. With the
            dawn of redeeming grace, Jesus, Lord, at thy birth. </dial><dial speak="SECOND CHORUS"
                ><spk>SECOND CHORUS</spk>. Sleep, Holy Babe, upon thy Mother’s breast; Great Lord of
            earth and sea and sky! How sweet it is to see thee lie In such a place of rest! Sleep
            holy Babe, thine angels watch around, * All bending low with folded wings, Before
            th’incarnate King of Kings. <sd>(The scene fades in darkness. A long silence. Three
                strokes of a bell)</sd>
        </dial><pn>10</pn>
    </scene>
    <scene n="3">
        <sceneNumb>SCENE III</sceneNumb>
        <desc>1912. CHRISTMAS ON THE BATTLEFIELDS</desc>
        <sd>(Where now arc “Peace on Earth, Good Will to Men?” In a ghastly gleam of red, soldiers
            in helmets, gas masks, marching, marching, marching, falling, dying. Red Cross Nurses
            minister to the wounded)</sd> SONG OF THE SOLDIERS. <desc>(The Rose of No Man’s Land)
            There’s a rose that grows on No Man’s Land, And it's wonderful to see; Tho’dimmed with
            tears It will live for years In my garden of memory. It’s the one red rose the soldier
            knows, It’s the work of the Master’s hand; Mid War’s great curse Stands the Red Cross
            Nurse: She’s the Rose of No Man’s Land.</desc>
        <dial speak="THE NURSES"><spk>THE NURSES</spk>. <sd>(Holding their arms aloft)</sd> Lord God
            of Love, let us have peace! From W ar’s vain sacrifice Give us release. Grant Peace the
            victories War cannot know. God of the Ages! Hast Thou not seen Thy fields and meadows
            green Red with the blood of men where W ar hath been? Dost Thou not know War's fearful
            endless roll— The countless graves of those who paid the toll ? Teach us to build. Oh
            gentle Lord, not to destroy. Forge these bleeding swords into plowshares, II thy fields
            to increase: Lord of the lives to be—Let us have peace! <sd>(They kneel)</sd> God of the
            fatherless, we pray to Thee, Father of all of us. hear Thou our plea; Peace and Good
            Will to men are willed by Thee— Lord God of Love, Let us have Peace! </dial><dial
            speak="QUARTETTE"><spk>QUARTETTE</spk>. <sd>(Softly)</sd>. Peace, perfect peace, in this
            dark world of sin? The blood of Jesus whispers Peace within. Peace, perfect peace, with
            sorrows surging; round? On Jesus’ bosom naught but calm is found. Peace, perfect peace,
            with loved ones far away? In Jesus’ keeping we are safe, and they. Peace, perfect peace,
            our future all unknown? Jesus we know and He is oil the throne. Peace, perfect peace,
            death shadowing us and ours? Jesus has vanquished death and all its powers. Once more on
            the darkened stage there appears the shining way of the Angel, who spreads protecting
            zciitgs over the sisters <sd>(sleeping center)</sd>. Nurses still kneeling L, Soldiers
            R. Angel, clczvted center, over children. Angel sings with deep significance and
            tenderness: He shall feed His flock like a shepherd: He shall gather the lambs with his
            arm, and carry them in His bosom, and shall gently lead those that are with young. After
            the Angel's song of promise, Nurses and Soldiers, inspired with hope and courage, burst
            forth in a triumphal strain. </dial><pn>12</pn>
        <dial speak="CHORUS"><spk>CHORUS</spk>. Ring out, wild bells, to the wild sky, The flying
            cloud, the frosty light; The year is dying in the night; Ring out, wild bells, and let
            him die. Ring out the old, ring in the new, Ring happy bells, across the snow; The year
            is going, let him go ; Ring out the false, ring in the true. Ring out the grief that
            saps the mind, For those that here we see no more; Ring out the feud of rich and poor,
            Ring in redress to all mankind. Ring out the want, the care, the sin, The faithless
            coldness of the times; Ring out, ring out my mournful rhymes, But ring the fuller
            minstrel in. Ring out the shapes of foul disease, Ring out the narrowing lust of gold:
            Ring out the thousand wars of o ld : Ring in the thousand years of peace! Ring in the
            valiant man and free, The larger heart, the kindlier hand; Ring out the darkness of the
            land, Ring in the Christ that is to be ! The Christmas Chimes, which have been playing
            throughout the hymn, as if in the distance, now peal forth in a loud and joyful clamor.
            After which darkness, and again a silence.</dial>
        <pn>13</pn>
    </scene>
    <scene n="4">
        <sceneNumb>SCENE IV (as in Scene I)</sceneNumb>
        <sd>The children are discovered asleep at their prayer.</sd><dial speak="HANNAH">
            <spk>HANNAH</spk> (Arousing herself): Twelve o’clock! Dear me! Almost time for Mother to
            come home, and Annikins hasn’t been put to bed! W hat will Mother say! <sd>(Staring in
                front of her as if dazed)</sd> But I have had a most wonderful dream! I thought I
                saw—<sd>(rubs her eyes as if trying to make sure she’s awake. Turns to waken the
                other children)</sd> Annikins! Nannettc! wake up ! Wake up, Dear. We ought to have
            been in bed long ago!</dial>
        <dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>. <sd>(rubbing her eyes and looking around—points
                center)</sd>: Christ Child! He was wight dere—’cause I seen Him!
            <spk>NANNETTE</spk>: I dreamed I saw Daddy marching and the Angel was bringing him home
            to us. Hannah gives her a startled, half incredulous look.</dial>
        <dial speak="NANNETTE"><spk>NANNETTE</spk>, <sd>(Arguing the point)</sd>: Well, didn’t you
            say that the Christ Child would come to us if we tried to be kind and good? And didn’t
            He say He loved little children and wanted them to come to Him? And didn’t we ask Him to
            come to us just a little while ago?</dial>
        <dial speak="HANNAH"><spk>HANNAH</spk>, <sd>(slozvly and dreamily</sd>). Yes, Dear—and may
            be— <sd>(Mother enters)</sd> Oh Mama! <sd>(Conscience stricken as she remembers her
                charges)</sd>. <spk>NANNETTE</spk>: Oh Momsie! We've got a Christmas tree! <sd>(The
                Mother soothes her excited children and takes Annikins in her arms.)</sd>
        </dial><pn>14</pn>
        <dial speak="ANNIKINS"><spk>ANNIKINS</spk>: An’—An’ Muvver! Christ Child Come! He brought me
            some sugar! </dial>
        <sd type="italics">The tree is mysteriously alight. It glotus marvelously as the curtain
            slozuly descends.</sd>
        <desc type="bold">TABLEAU</desc>
        <pn>35</pn>
    </scene>
</xml>
